A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs, Series Q FA326
Rockefeller Archive Center
- War Relief
  - War Relief - European Relief Appeals, 1917-1930 (Box 38, Folder 326)
    Small gifts by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to French wounded and orphaned children. Quakers aid to Russia, 1927. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel.
    98
  - War Relief - European Relief Appeals - American Committee for Devastated France, 1922-1923 (Box 38, Folder 327)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined permission to have unicorn tapestries displayed to raise money for France. Gave $2,000 instead. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur Woods.
    98.3
  - War Relief - European Relief Appeals - Jewish War Relief, 1918-1922 (Box 38, Folder 328)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined to contribute, 1918-1921, believing that all aid should be solely on humanitarian lines rather than through racial appeals. But in 1922 he contributed $10,000 to Brooklyn campaign. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - War Relief - European Relief Appeals - Bulgarian Earthquake Relief, 1928-1930 (Box 39, Folder 329)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed to fund through Red Cross. Sent $2,000 to aid student of H. S. Fosdick to rebuild his house in Bulgaria. Further personal appeals declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., H. E. Fosdick, Arthur Woods.
  - War Relief - European Relief Appeals - China Famine Committee, 1920-1921 (Box 39, Folder 330)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Laurance S. Rockefeller contribute $500,000 to China famine relief. Laurance S. Rockefeller underwrote additional $500,000 loan from bank to make funds immediately available. Additional $750,000 underwritten by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Starr J. Murphy. All loans paid off by Famine fund. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., S. D. Murphy, T. W. Lamont.
  - War Relief - War Relief Appeals, 1939-1944 (Box 39, Folder 331)
    Wide variety of appeals from various agencies asking for aid to help suffering in Europe and Korea. Most declined. A few small token gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
  - War Relief - War Relief Appeals, 1945-1947 (Box 39, Folder 332)
  - War Relief - War Relief Appeals, 1948-1957 (Box 39, Folder 333)
    DR material removed to Folder 333A.
  - War Relief - War Relief Appeals, 1941-1947 (Box 39, Folder 0333A)
    Wide variety of appeals from various agencies asking for aid to help suffering in Europe and Korea. Most declined. A few small token gifts. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - War Relief - International Rescue and Relief Committee, 1949-1961 (Box 39, Folder 0333B)
    98.18
  - War Relief - European War Appeals - Miscellaneous Folders - Affidavits, etc. for Refugees, 1940-1942 (Box 39, Folder 334)
    Endorsing refugees for United States entry.
  - War Relief - European War Appeals - Miscellaneous Folders - American Friends of Yugoslavia, 1942-1946 (Box 39, Folder 335)
    No Rockefeller contribution.
  - War Relief - European War Appeals - Miscellaneous Folders - Norway Appeals, 1940-1943 (Box 39, Folder 336)
    No Rockefeller action.
  - War Relief - European War Appeals - Miscellaneous Folders - Dr. Van Zeeland, 1939 (Box 39, Folder 337)
    Scheme for settlement of refugees; no Rockefeller action.
  - War Relief - European War Appeals - Miscellaneous Folders - Queen Wilhelmina Fund, 1940-1947 (Box 39, Folder 338)
    Nelson A. Rockefeller gives $1,000 anonymously, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. $5,000 in 1942, $5,000 in 1947.
  - War Relief - European War Appeals - Miscellaneous Folders - Vienna Children's Milk Relief, 1920-1924 (Box 39, Folder 339)
    Mr. and Mrs. Kriesler appealed to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. for aid. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. bought tickets to benefit concerts, gave $100 annually, 1922-1924, toward support. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
  - War Relief Appeals - Foster Parents Plan for War Children, 1940-1954 (Box 39, Folder 340)
    Plan to support orphaned children overseas. Appeals declined.
  - War Relief Appeals - Medical Aid Pledge November 16, 1939, 1939-1940 (Box 39, Folder 341)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller gave $2,500 for Society for British Medical Aid. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $50,000.
  - War Relief Appeals - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc., 1941-1957 (Box 39, Folder 342)
    Appeals declined.
  - War Relief - British War Relief Society - Contributions, 1940-1941 (Box 40, Folder 343)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $50,000; also other small gifts from him and other members of the family. John D. Rockefeller 3rd and W. W. Aldrich on board. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    98.1
  - War Relief - British War Relief Society - Contributions - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Contribution, 1940, 1940-1943 (Box 40, Folder 344)
    Money, used wearing apparel, blankets, small and large gifts.
  - War Relief - Allied Relief Fund, 1940-1945 (Box 40, Folder 345)
    Invitations to dinners, reports on work and organization. Merger with British War Relief Society. Appeals for Rockefeller participation in fund drives. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Winthrop Aldrich.
  - War Relief - United States Committee for Care of European Children, 1940-1953 (Box 40, Folder 346)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd on Committee for evacuation of children. Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd. Appeals to support drives. Report on work. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Marshall Field, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    98.1A
  - War Relief - British War Relief - Miscellaneous Appeals, 1939-1945 (Box 40, Folder 347)
    Most declined. A few small gifts made. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    98.1B
  - War Relief - British War Relief - Miscellaneous Appeals - Royal Air Force Benevolent Fund, 1941-1943 (Box 40, Folder 348)
    Contribution by Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - War Relief - Bundles for Britain, 1940-1942 (Box 40, Folder 349)
    Small family contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    98.1B1
  - War Relief - Finnish Relief, 1939-1940 (Box 40, Folder 350)
    Family contributions to various Finnish Relief organizations. Shifting status of Finland in world affairs. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Herbert Hoover.
    98.2
  - War Relief - Finnish Relief - Pledge; February 21, 1940, 1939-1940 (Box 40, Folder 351)
    Gift of $100,000 from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and family.
  - War Relief - Finnish Relief - Letters of Appreciation, 1940 (Box 40, Folder 352)
    Regarding $100,000 gift.
  - War Relief - Ambulance Fund Contributions, 1917-1919 (Box 41, Folder 353)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $1,000 toward Columbia University Ambulance Corps, $100 to Sleepy Hollow Ambulance Corps. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson.
  - War Relief - Ambulance and Hospital Unit Organization, 1939-1942 (Box 41, Folder 354)
    Preparation in France for aerial bombing. Appeals for aid declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - War Relief - Ambulance and Hospital Unit Organization - British-American Ambulance Corps Appeals, 1940-1942 (Box 41, Folder 355)
    Declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
  - War Relief - Near East Relief Committee, 1896-1925 (Box 41, Folder 356)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. contributions to Armenians suffering from Moslem persecution, 1896. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions to needy Armenians in 1916. Report on Near East conditions. The refugees of 1920-1925. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson.
    98.4
  - War Relief - Near East Foundation (Also Near East Relief - Golden Rule), 1923-1929 (Box 41, Folder 357)
    Rockefeller family participated one Sunday in frugal meal; usual additional cost of regular meal contributed to aid orphans in New East. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution. John D. Rockefeller 3rd declines membership. Foundation and memorial gift. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget.
  - War Relief - Near East Foundation (Also Near East Relief - Golden Rule), 1930-1954 (Box 41, Folder 358)
  - War Relief - Golden Rule Foundation, 1929-1953 (Box 41, Folder 359)
    To foster peace, religion and love throughout the world. Requests for contributions declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    98.5
  - War Relief - Golden Rule Foundation - American Mothers' Committee, 1943-1952 (Box 41, Folder 360)
  - War Relief - American Relief Administration, 1920-1923 (Box 41, Folder 361)
    Herbert Hoover's relief program for European children. Laurance S. Rockefeller, Rockefeller Foundation and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $1,000,000 each. Hoover comments on aid to Russia in 1923. Herbert Hoover, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    98.6
  - War Relief - Polish Relief, 1939-1946 (Box 41, Folder 362)
    Appeals declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
  - War Relief - Greek War Relief, 1940-1953 (Box 41, Folder 363)
    Appeal for aid declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    98.7
  - War Relief - Greek War Relief - Contributions, 1940-1947 (Box 41, Folder 364)
    Family contributions: $30,000 from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in 1940 and 1941. $26,000 from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in 1947. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - War Relief - Greek War Relief - Organizations, 1940-1949 (Box 41, Folder 365)
    Appeals declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard
    98.71
  - War Relief - Russian Relief, 1921-1929 (Box 42, Folder 366)
    Appeals for aid to Russians both in and outside of Russia. Declined. Appeal for aid in education of Russian emigre children. Correspondents include Arthur Woods, Kenneth Chorley, Willard S. Richardson.
  - War Relief - Russian Relief - American Committee for Constantinople Russian Refugees, 1930-1936 (Box 42, Folder 367)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $5,000. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
  - War Relief - Russian Relief Through Princess Cantacuzene, 1920-1930 (Box 42, Folder 368)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed anonymously through the Princess toward relief of Russian refugees. A large part of work done in Warsaw by Russian Red Cross. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions apparently supported most of the relief work conducted in Poland. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Princess Cantacuzene.
  - War Relief - Committee for the Education of Russian Youth in Exile, 1919-1929 (Box 42, Folder 369)
    Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - War Relief - American Committee for the Relief of German Children, 1922-1924 (Box 42, Folder 370)
    A Quaker project. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $5,000 in 1923; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $25,000 in 1924. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Beardsley Ruml.
    98.8
  - War Relief - American Aid and Relief Organization, 1943-1959 (Box 42, Folder 371)
    Appeals for gifts to aid refugees. Most declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - War Relief - American Aid and Relief Organization - Navy Relief Society, 1942-1945 (Box 42, Folder 372)
    Small family gifts.
  - War Relief - United Seamen's Service, 1942-1961 (Box 42, Folder 373)
    Providing shore, leisure time activities for men of the merchant marine. Appeals declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    98.81
  - War Relief - United Seamen's Service - Clippings, 1942-1949 (Box 42, Folder 374)
  - War Relief - American Overseas Aid - United Nations Appeal for Children, 1947-1949 (Box 42, Folder 375)
    Appeal declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    98.82
  - War Relief - Russian Relief, 1941-1949 (Box 43, Folder 376)
    Study of Russian Relief organizations. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $50,000; Rockefeller Brothers Fund contributed $10,000. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Alan Wardwell, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., E. C. Carter.
    98.9
  - War Relief - Russian Relief - Contributions, 1942 (Box 43, Folder 377)
  - War Relief - Victory Clothing Collection for Overseas Relief, 1945-1946 (Box 43, Folder 378)
    Nelson A. Rockefeller was New York chairman for drive; comments on drive. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Frank Jamieson.
    98.10
    See also Box 43A, Folder 378A.
  - War Relief - World Food Situation, 1946-1951 (Box 43, Folder 379)
    Appeals for contributions toward food for needy in world. Most declined. A few small family donations to local organizations.
    98.12
  - War Relief - American Aid to France, 1945-1950 (Box 43, Folder 380)
    Organization to help post-war France. Family contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller.
    98.13
  - War Relief - American Aid to France, 1945-1950 (Box 43, Folder 0380A)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted from scholarly access.
  - War Relief - American Aid to France - Contributions, 1946-1947 (Box 43, Folder 381)
  - War Relief - American Friends of France, 1946-1955 (Box 43, Folder 382)
    David Rockefeller made contributions through organization for health and education work in France. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, David Rockefeller.
    98.14
  - War Relief - American Friends of France, 1946-1955 (Box 43, Folder 0382A)
  - War Relief - American Relief for Italy, Inc., 1946-1959 (Box 43, Folder 383)
    Appeals for general aid and for Italian boys towns. Rockefeller Brothers Fund makes $5,000 contribution; other requests declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    98.15
  - War Relief - Marshall Plan, 1947-1951 (Box 43, Folder 384)
    Campaign to secure passage of Plan through Congress. John D. Rockefeller 3rd and Nelson A. Rockefeller contributed. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    98.16
  - War Relief - Marshall Plan - Contributions, 1947-1948 (Box 43, Folder 385)
  - War Relief - Victory Clothing Collection for Overseas Relief - Index Cards, 1945-1946 (Box 043A, Folder 0378A)
    See also Box 43, Folder 378.
  - War Relief - Victory Clothing Collection for Overseas Relief - Index Cards, 1945-1946 (Box 043A, Folder 0378A)
  - War Relief - International Rescue and Relief Committee, 1943-1954 (Box 44, Folder 386)
    Relief, evacuation and rehabilitation of refugees. Many appeals declined. Request by John J. McCloy in 1953. Nelson A. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, 3rd's gifts. Contribution to Hungarian appeal, Medico. Correspondents include Yorke Allen, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Angier B. Duke.
  - War Relief - International Rescue and Relief Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 44, Folder 387)
    DR material removed to Folder 387A.
  - War Relief - International Rescue and Relief Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 44, Folder 0387A)
    David Rockefeller's gifts. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - War Relief - International Rescue and Relief Committee, 1957-1961 (Box 44, Folder 388)
  - War Relief - Resettlement Campaign for Exiled Professionals, 1950-1951 (Box 44, Folder 389)
    Appeals declined. Correspondents include Reinhold Niebuhr, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    98.181
  - War Relief - Resettlement Campaign for Exiled Professionals, 1950-1951 (Box 44, Folder 0389A)
  - War Relief - Iron Curtain Refugee Campaign, 1949-1952 (Box 44, Folder 390)
    Appeals to Family declined. Correspondents include R. Byrd, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    98.182
  - War Relief - Iron Curtain Refugee Campaign, 1949-1952 (Box 44, Folder 0390A)
  - War Relief - Operation Brotherhood, 1955 (Box 44, Folder 391)
    Junior Chamber of Commerce program of aid for South Viet Nam. John D. Rockefeller 3rd made several small gifts. Large Filipino role in work in Vietnam. John D. Rockefeller 3rd gave $25,000 through International Rescue Committee; $15,000 in 1957 for work in Laos. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dana S. Creel.
    98.183
    DR material removed to Folder 391A.
  - War Relief - Operation Brotherhood, 1955 (Box 44, Folder 0391A)
    Junior Chamber of Commerce program of aid for South Viet Nam. David Rockefeller refused to serve on board. David Rockefeller made several small gifts. Large Filipino role in work in Vietnam. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - War Relief - Operation Brotherhood, 1956-1959 (Box 44, Folder 392)
  - War Relief - Medico, 1958-1961 (Box 44, Folder 393)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's interest and contributions. His interest in Southeast Asia, Dr. Dooley's work. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Freeman, Thomas Dooley, David Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Angier B. Duke.
    98.184
  - War Relief - Medico, 1958-1961 (Box 44, Folder 0393A)
  - War Relief - American Middle East Relief, Inc., 1948-1961 (Box 45, Folder 394)
    Organization set up to help displaced Palestinian Arabs. No family contribution. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    98.19
  - War Relief - American Middle East Relief, Inc., 1948-1961 (Box 45, Folder 0394A)
  - War Relief - American Medical Center for Burma, Inc., 1947-1961 (Box 45, Folder 395)
    Requests for aid. John D. Rockefeller 3rd's contributions. Correspondents include Gordon Seagrave, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dr. McCracken, David McKendree Key.
    98.191
  - War Relief - McCloy Project - German Rehabilitation, 1950-1952 (Box 45, Folder 396)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gift approximately $25,000. Pledge up to $100,000, lapsed in 1952. Originated as John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to John J. McCloy. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John J. McCloy, Dana S. Creel.
    98.20
  - War Relief - Medical and Surgical Relief Committee, Inc., 1941-1955 (Box 45, Folder 397)
    To send medical supplies to hospitals which give free medical aid. No contribution except some medical supplies from apartment. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel.
    98.21
  - War Relief - American Field Services, Inc., 1940-1954 (Box 45, Folder 398)
    To provide ambulances during war. Various requests. 1949-1950 International scholarships program. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Stephen Galatti.
    98.31
  - War Relief - Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe, Inc. (CARE), 1946-1961 (Box 45, Folder 399)
    Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe (CARE) activities.
    98.121
  - War Relief - Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe, Inc. (CARE), 1946-1961 (Box 45, Folder 399A)
- National War Fund
  - National War Fund, 1942-1957 (Box 45, Folder 400)
    A united-appeal organization to raise funds for United Service Organizations (USO) and British War Relief, as well as "peacetime" agencies such as Boy Scouts, hospitals, etc. Arthur W. Packard assisted in initial organization; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. honorary New York chairman. Fund received $321,000,000 in contributions. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Winthrop Aldrich, H. J. Seymour.
    123
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1943-1947 (Box 45, Folder 401)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. concerned about relationship between United Service Organizations (USO) and National War Fund. Helps clarify relations between fund and "peacetime" agencies. Objects to use of hatred in campaign literature. Given award by President's War Relief Control Board. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., H. W. Wriston, Mrs. H. A. Ingraham.
    123.1
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses, 1943-1945 (Box 46, Folder 402)
    Copies of addresses given in New York City, Detroit, Minneapolis and Chicago. Radio address prepared at end of war. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    123.2
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - National War Fund State Chairmen and Leaders Conference, 1943 (Box 46, Folder 403)
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - Chicago Community and War Fund, 1943 (Box 46, Folder 404)
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - Open Meeting - Women's Division, 1943-1949 (Box 46, Folder 405)
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - Phonograph Record Talk, 1943-1945 (Box 46, Folder 406)
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - Minneapolis, 1944-1945 (Box 46, Folder 407)
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - New York War Fund Annual Meeting, 1945 (Box 46, Folder 408)
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - Detroit Address, 1945-1946 (Box 46, Folder 409)
  - National War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - Commerce and Industry Luncheon, 1945-1946 (Box 46, Folder 410)
  - National War Fund - Contributions, 1943-1946 (Box 46, Folder 411)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gives $300,000, in 1943, 1944, 1945; Abby Aldrich Rockefeller gives $50,000. Winthrop Rockefeller gives $25,000 anonymously. $90,000 contributed by Rockefeller Brothers Fund; other smaller gifts by members of the family. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Winthrop Aldrich.
    123.3
  - National War Fund - New York War Fund, 1943-1946 (Box 46, Folder 412)
    Local Branch of National Organization. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. served as honorary chairman until organization formally incorporated. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Emil Schram.
    123.4
  - National War Fund - New York War Fund - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Membership, 1943-1945 (Box 46, Folder 413)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s participation as honorary chairman.
  - National War Fund - New York War Fund - Contributions, 1943-1946 (Box 46, Folder 414)
    By John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Rockefeller Brothers Fund, and other members of the family.